Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series VIII: Fidel: The Untold Story and Anecdotes about Fidel, 1995-2002; 477042
  - Castro, Fidel: End of Speech in Mandela Park, Jamaica, circa 1998; cuid18145; 467947 (Box 6, Cassette ref106, Box 97, Dvd ref106)
    This video features the end of a speech by Fidel Castro in Mandela Park in Kingston, Jamaica. In this portion of the speech Castro discusses the need for Caribbean solidarity as a way to promote education and economic development in the region. He also calls for a greater dedication to the preservation of natural resources, protection of the environment, and support of neighbors after natural disasters such as hurricanes. At the end of the speech Castro is presented with a gift to thank him for visiting the city.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:15:19.
  - "Plaza - Sam Sharpe - Montego Bay", circa 1998; cuid18146; 467937 (Box 6, Cassette ref116, Box 97, Dvd ref116)
    This video features on-the-street interviews with crowds waiting for the arrival of Fidel Castro. In a series of brief interviews Estela Bravo asks individuals why they have come to see Castro speak and their opinions about him as a leader. Many express their admiration for Castro, specifically citing Cuba's role as a leader in education and healthcare in the Caribbean.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 0:24:54.
  - Crowd Footage: Castro Speech at Sam Sharpe Square in Montego Bay, Jamaica, circa 1998; cuid18147; 467909 (Box 6, Cassette ref144, Box 97, Dvd ref144)
    This video features footage of crowds in Montego Bay, Jamaica watching a speech by Fidel Castro. The footage focuses predominantly on individuals and their reactions to Castro's speech. Castro speaks in Spanish while his translator speaks in English, but the audio is only present in the background, while the video focuses predominantly on members of the crowd. The video starts and stops several times and as a result does not contain a complete recording of Castro's speech.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:19:59.
  - Grenada; Fidel Hotel Pegaso with Jamaican Governor, circa 1998; cuid18148; 467928 (Box 6, Cassette ref125)
  - News footage - Pierre Trudeau, etc., undated; cuid18149; 479371 (Box 62, Cassette ref1032)
  - Parts of Interview Translated Into English, 2001; cuid18150; 590732 (Box 72, Folder 20-21)
  - "Pastors for Peace" Caravan Footage - Miami, Little Havana, 1993 July 15, 1993 July 17; cuid18151; 477143 (Box 69, Cassette ref886, Box 85, Dvd ref886)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:20.
  - "Pastors for Peace" Caravan Footage in Miami, 1993 July 16; cuid18152; 479320 (Box 46, Cassette ref1002)
  - "Pastors for Peace" Caravan Footage in Miami, 1993 July 16; cuid18153; 479332 (Box 46, Cassette ref1006)
  - "Pastors for Peace" Caravan Footage in Miami, includes Lucius Walker, 1993 July 17; cuid18154; 479323 (Box 62, Cassette ref1003)
    This tape is potentially damaged or unviewable.
  - "Pastors for Peace" Caravan Footage in Miami, 1993 July 16; cuid18155; 467981 (Box 3, Cassette ref72)
  - "Photos of Rangel, Mandela, Clinton, El Papa, and Hotel Teresa", 1996 August 10; cuid18156; 468034 (Box 2, Cassette ref19)
  - Photos of Alicia Alonso, Ramon Castro, Fidel Castro, Leonel Soto, Samora Machel, and Others, circa 1995-2000; cuid18157; 467979 (Box 2, Cassette ref74, Box 97, Dvd ref74)
    This video features still images of Fidel Castro and an interview with Cuban revolutionary Lionel Soto. The first 10 minutes features shots of still images of Castro with members of his family, including his oldest brother Ramón and his mother Lina Ruz González. Later photos feature Castro speaking to Cuban dancer Alicia Alonso after one of her performances. At minute 10:10 the video changes to an interview with Lionel Soto. Soto speaks about his memories of Castro and the student activist movement at the University of Havana. He describes student activism in period leading up to the Cuban revolution and Castro's role as a leader of that movement.
  - Presenting Fidel Documentary in Los Angeles, circa 2001; TW_TAM_616_ER_8
  - Riverside Church, Harlem: Castro Speech (part 1), 2000 September 8; cuid376; 479367 (Box 47, Cassette ref1028, Box 96, Dvd ref1028)
    This video features footage of Fidel Castro's 2000 visit to the Riverside Church in the Harlem. The footage begins with a short speech by Bronx Congressman Jose Serrano welcoming Castro the New York City. The first 14-minutes feature individuals welcoming Castro and the crowd cheering for him and singing "Happy Birthday." At minute 14:30 Castro addresses the crowd and thanks them for their hospitality. He discusses his previous visits to New York City, and talks about several social issues like the blockade against Cuba, and maternal deaths and child malnutrition in the third world.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:18.
  - Riverside Church, Harlem: Castro Speech (part 2), 2000 September 8; cuid377; 479368 (Box 47, Cassette ref1029, Box 96, Dvd ref1029)
    This video features the continuation of Fidel Castro's speech at Riverside Church in Harlem. In this portion of the speech Castro discusses the trade embargo and the effect it has had on Cuba's ability to obtain food and medicine. He also criticizes the globalized banking system and the problem of professionals from the third world moving to richer nations. He discusses Cuban solidarity with third world nations in Latin America and Africa, and praises the quality education and medical care in Cuba. This video stops and starts several times and does not contain a complete recording of the speech.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:34.
  - Riverside Church, Harlem: Castro in New York (part 1), 2000 September 8; cuid378; 479391 (Box 62, Cassette ref1052, Box 96, Dvd ref1052)
    This video features footage from Fidel Castro's visit to the Riverside Church in Harlem in the year 2000. The bulk of the video features footage of the crowd waiting for Castro's arrival. At minute 1:55 Estela Bravo briefly interviews Bronx Congressman Jose Serrano about his opinions of Castro and the reason the crowd at the church is eager to hear him speak. At minute 10:16 the footage changes to an interview with an American diplomat who was part of the negotiations to return Elian González to Cuba. She talks about Castro as a negotiator and her perceptions of working with him on the González case. The footage also shows Fidel Castro arriving at the church and brief welcoming statements from various speakers.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:30:02.
  - "Riverside Church, Harlem (part 4), circa 1995-2000; cuid18158; 479395 (Box 62, Cassette ref1056)
  - Riverside Church, Harlem (part 5), circa 1995-2000; cuid18159; 467824 (Box 10, Cassette ref229, Box 97, Dvd ref229)
    This video features the final portion of Fidel Castro's speech at Riverside Church in Harlem. In this segment he thanks the American people who called for Elián González's return to Cuba, and those who protested legislation strengthening the trade embargo against Cuba. Castro then speaks about inequality and marginalization, which he acknowledges continues to exist in Cuba, and pledges his commitment to ending poor housing conditions and raising standards of living. Finally, he talks at length about what he viewed as overblown news coverage of his handshake with American President Bill Clinton, explaining that it lasted only a brief moment and the two men were simply trying to be polite.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:14.
  - Jesse Helms News Conference (part 1), 1995 February 9; cuid18160; 467816 (Box 10, Cassette ref237, Box 97, Dvd ref237)
    This video features a press conference hosted by United States senators and congressional representatives introducing the Cuban Liberty and Democratic Solidarity Act, later called the Helms-Burton Act. Senator Jesse Helms of South Carolina introduces the act and the goals of the legislation. Helms expresses his hope that the bill will lead to an end of Fidel Castro's leadership in Cuba and lead the country on a path away from communism. Co-author of the bill, Representative Dan Burton from Indiana speaks next and outlines the provisions of the bill, which places restrictions on U.S. trading partners who seek to trade with Cuba. Burton stresses the bi-partisan support for the bill and the stated goal of hastening the end of Fidel Castro's control in Cuba. Other speakers include representatives who contributed to the bill Lincoln Díaz-Balart, Bob Menendez, and Ileana Ros-Lehtinen.
  - Jesse Helms News Conference (part 2), 1995 February 9; cuid18161; 467828 (Box 10, Cassette ref225, Box 97, Dvd ref225)
    This video features a press conference with United States senators announcing the passage of the Cuban Liberty and Democratic Solidarity (Libertad) Act of 1996 also known as the Helms-Burton Act. Footage begins with a brief statement by Democratic Representative Robert Menendez of New Jersey, followed by a congressman from Florida, both of whom celebrate the bipartisan nature of the bill and express their hope that the bill will ultimately lead to the end of Fidel Castro's leadership in Cuba. Senator Jesse Helms ends the press conference describing the provisions of the bill, the restrictions it places on trade with Cuba, and expresses his hope that the bill will expedite the removal of Fidel Castro from power in Cuba.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:12:53.
  - Script, undated; cuid18162; 590733 (Box 72, Folder 23)
  - Selection of Images "Yo Estuve Alli/ I Was There" (ICAIC), 2000 August 29; cuid18163; 477202 (Box 70, Cassette ref943, Box 85, Dvd ref943)
    According to Estela Bravo, this footage is a black and white documentary about the history of Cuba. This footage is not originally from one of Bravo's documentaries, but she used clips from it for her film Fidel.
  - State Council Footage: Scenes of Birán and other Fidel-related "Universidad Fidel de Casselle", undated; cuid18164; 467856 (Box 9, Cassette ref197)
  - State Council Footage: "Speeches Create Conscience", undated; cuid18165; 479362 (Box 62, Cassette ref1023)
  - State Council Footage: Includes footage in Chile, Colombia, and with Mohammed Ali, undated; cuid18166; 477187 (Box 71, Cassette ref928, Box 85, Dvd ref928)
    Much of the footage was filmed in Chile and Colombia. It contains an assortment of clips including: Castro meeting Latin American presidents; Gabriel García Márquez and his wife Mercedes; Castro speaking about inequality and justice; footage of Robert McNamara, Castro, and Jorge Risquet joking with each other around 00:27:00; a speech by Castro; and a celebration of Castro's birthday on plane. At 00:38:00 there is footage of a meeting in preparation for Pope's visit to Cuba. In another clip, Castro shows a set of Russian dolls and boxing puppets of himself and Bill Clinton, and around 00:56:00 there is a clip of a visit by Mohammed Ali and the Cuban boxer, Teofilo Stevenson. The sound drops out in intermittently throughout the video.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 01:04:49.
  - State Council Footage: Diane Sawyer, Dan Rather, and Others, 1998 August 7; cuid18167; 477188 (Box 71, Cassette ref929, Box 85, Dvd ref929)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 01:33:35.
  - State Council Footage: Fidel and Mandela, 1998 August 7; cuid18168; 477189 (Box 71, Cassette ref930, Box 85, Dvd ref930)
    The footage shows Fidel at the Rome Food and Agriculture Organization press conference in 1966; during visit to South Africa; at a reception line in Cuba; and in an interview with Diane Sawyer.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 01:31:33.
  - State Council Footage: Pope (part 1) (airport arrival, speeches, greetings, Fidel kissing the Pope), 1998; cuid18169; 477191 (Box 70, Cassette ref932, Box 85, Dvd ref932)
  - State Council Footage: Pope (part 2), 1998; cuid18170; 477192 (Box 70, Cassette ref933, Box 85, Dvd ref933)
  - State Council Footage: Pope (part 3), 1998; cuid18171; 479345 (Box 46, Cassette ref1010)
  - State Council Footage: Pope (part 4) (Dominican Cardinals), 1998; cuid18172; 479347 (Box 46, Cassette ref1011)
  - State Council Footage: ICAIC (The Cuban Institute of Cinematographic Art and Industry) Newsreels, undated; cuid18173; 477194 (Box 71, Cassette ref935, Box 85, Dvd ref935)
    There are a series of black and white clips on this tape. It contains older footage of Fidel Castro.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:10:01.
  - State Council Footage: ICAIC Newsreels, undated; cuid18174; 477195 (Box 71, Cassette ref936, Box 85, Dvd ref936)
    This tape contains a variety of black and white ICAIC film clips, which are in Spanish. They show Fidel Castro in many different settings such as state visits (including to Indira Gandhi), speeches, among the Cuban people, playing chess, hugging African leaders, and at a school. Some of the clips are older and some are duplicated on other footage.
  - State Council Footage: ICAIC Newsreels, circa 1980s; cuid18175; 477196 (Box 71, Cassette ref937, Box 85, Dvd ref937)
    This video includes five newsreels from ICAIC. They consist of a state visit by Mikhail Gorbachev; a visit by Jesse Jackson including a commemoration of Martin Luther King, Jr.; a brief piece of music and dancing; state visit by Socialist Spanish prime minister Felipe Marquez; and a commemoration of Cuban revolutionary fighter and intimate friend of Fidel Castro, Celia Sanchez.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:52:11.
  - State Council Footage: Archives ICRT, 1998 August 17; cuid18176; 477197 (Box 71, Cassette ref938, Box 85, Dvd ref938)
    This tape contains over an hour of very old clips and footage. The first 8-minute segment is from Edward R. Murrow's Person to Person television show with Fidel Castro and his son Fidelito. The footage that follows includes grainy clips of Havana after Batista fled Cuba and several shots of tourists leaving the country. These clips are mostly black and white and in some places there is no sound. Most are in Spanish, but there is a small amount of narration in English. There are also shots of enthusiastic crowds as Castro and his entourage travel through the countryside and into Havana. Some footage appears to have been shot in Harlem during Fidel's visit to the United Nations.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 01:03:40.
  - State Council Footage: Reception, Rockefeller Family in Havana, undated; cuid379; 467858 (Box 9, Cassette ref195, Box 96, Dvd ref195)
    This short clip features footage of Fidel Castro speaking to a group of people at a reception. Most of the people speak in English and Castro speaks to them through a translator. He engages in discussions with several individuals on a variety of topics including US trade, production of goods, and agriculture and the use of pesticides. In the second part of the clip Castro speaks to an older man about his approach to public speaking and the ways he tries to connect with the crowd.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:19:39.
  - State Council Footage: Elián González in school, circa 2000; cuid18177; 479378 (Box 62, Cassette ref1039)
  - State Council Footage: Farrakhan, [Louis], Pres Panama, [Juan] Almeida, Raul, Fidel, and others, undated; cuid18178; 477199 (Box 70, Cassette ref940, Box 85, Dvd ref940)
  - State Council Footage: Fidel Castro Speech "Africans in America Committee 1 of 2"; "Abyssinian Baptist Church", 1995 October 22; cuid18179; 477198 (Box 71, Cassette ref939, Box 85, Dvd ref939)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 01:02:21.
  - State Council Footage: South Africa, Jamaica, Barbados, and Grenada, undated; cuid799; 477200 (Box 71, Cassette ref941, Box 85, Dvd ref941)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 01:02:32.
  - State Council Footage: Wide variety including García Márquez, Che Guevara, and the Pope's visit to Cuba, 1998 November 18-22; cuid18180; 477201 (Box 67, Cassette ref942, Box 85, Dvd ref942)
    This tape features footage of individuals including Pope John Paul II, Gabriel García Márquez, and Che Guevara. It includes clips of Fidel Castro visiting his home in Biran with García Márquez, talking about his youth, and planning the Pope's visit. Scenes also include speeches by Castro, and Cuban television recordings from the revolutionary period before the fall of Fulgencio Batista. Around 00:57:00 there is black and white footage from 1959 featuring post revolution celebrations, motorcades, and footage of Che Guevara. This footage includes speeches by Guevara and scenes of him performing charity work.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 01:32:45.
  - State Council Footage: Fidel presents "honorary degree", undated; cuid18181; 479327 (Box 62, Cassette ref1004)
  - State Council Footage: Cuando Pienso en el Che, Cuban Missile Crisis, and Bay of Pigs, undated; cuid380; 467878 (Box 8, Cassette ref175, Box 96, Dvd ref175)
    This video features Cuban television footage about the life of Ernesto "Che" Guevara, and the Cuban Missile Crisis. The first 35 minutes of the tape feature a program titled "Cuando pienso en el Che," in which Fidel Castro shares his memories of Guevara. Castro speaks about Guevara's role during the Cuban Revolution, his work in the Cuban government, and his pursuit of revolutionary movements in Africa and Latin America. Beginning at minute 35:45 the tape changes to footage of Cuban news reports and historical footage from the Cuban Missile Crisis and the Bay of Pigs invasion.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 01:02:52.
  - State Council Footage: "Filosofia de Fidel" Transfers, 1998 July; cuid18182; 479337 (Box 46, Cassette ref1008)
  - State Council Footage: Fidel Castro/South African Parliament, 1998 April 9; cuid18183; 479339 (Box 46, Cassette ref1009, Box 97, Dvd ref1009)
    This video features a speech by Fidel Castro at the Parliament of South Africa. The beginning of the video begins with representatives entering the chamber and welcoming Castro. Portions of this speech are duplicated on the video ref150. Duplicated content runs approximately from minute 12:00 to 41:00. After minute 41:00 Castro continues speaking about the potential of African youth and stresses Cuba's history of solidarity with African nations and the third world. He addresses challenges facing Africa like deforestation, desertification, and HIV/AIDS. The end of the video focuses on speculative investment and the United States economy, in which Castro criticizes the US for artificially inflating its currency. Video and audio quality of this recording is very poor.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:02:39.
  - State Council Footage: Fidel Castro at the United Nations, undated; cuid18184; 479366 (Box 62, Cassette ref1027)
  - State Council Footage: "UNTV Castro visit to UN;" Clinton Speech, 1995 November 22; cuid18185; 467888 (Box 7, Cassette ref165)
  - State Council Footage: Fidel Castro Speech Abyssinian Baptist Church, undated; cuid18186; 467890 (Box 7, Cassette ref163)
  - State Council Footage: Castro Visits Harlem, 1995 October 22; cuid381; 479356 (Box 47, Cassette ref1017, Box 95, Dvd ref1017)
    This video features footage of Fidel Castro at the Abyssinian Baptist Church in Harlem in 1995. The footage largely consists of shots of the crowd chanting " Cuba Sí, Bloqueo No," and some notable individuals can be seen in the crowd including Angela Davis and Ricardo Alarcón. The video contains several segments of speakers welcoming Castro to Harlem, but much of the footage of the speakers is cut short. The end of the recording shows Castro leaving the church and greeting the crowd.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:28.
  - State Council Footage: "Images Harlem and Hotel Teresa", undated; cuid18187; 467867 (Box 9, Cassette ref186)
  - State Council Footage: Harlem (part 1), 1995 October 23; cuid18188; 467864 (Box 9, Cassette ref189)
  - State Council Footage: Harlem (part 2), undated; cuid18189; 467863 (Box 9, Cassette ref190)
  - State Council Footage: Interviews in Harlem, undated; cuid18190; 467862 (Box 9, Cassette ref191)
  - State Council Footage: Fidel Castro in Harlem, undated; cuid18191; 467859 (Box 9, Cassette ref194)
  - State Council Footage: Harlem Protesters, undated; cuid18192; 467848 (Box 9, Cassette ref205)
  - State Council Footage: Fidel in NY UN 50th Anniversary, 1998 July; cuid382; 479349 (Box 46, Cassette ref1012, Box 96, Dvd ref1012)
    This video features a portion of a speech by Fidel Castro's at the Abyssinian Baptist Church in Harlem, NY. The footage begins part-way through Castro's speech. He describes his decision to wear his military fatigues in Harlem, the unwelcoming reception he received from New York's political leaders, and the need to end the blockade on Cuba. He also talks about Cuba's support of independence struggles in Angola and South Africa, and the United Nations lack of recognition for their support. After Castro's speech concludes, footage shows him leaving the church and greeting members of the crowd.
  - State Council Footage: United Nations 50th Anniversary, undated; cuid18193; 467866 (Box 9, Cassette ref187)
  - State Council Footage: UN Russian (Boris Yeltsin) and Cuban (Fidel Castro) Presidents' Speeches, 1995 October 25; cuid18194; 467865 (Box 9, Cassette ref188)
  - State Council Footage: Fidel and Brezhnev, undated; cuid18195; 467851 (Box 9, Cassette ref202)
  - State Council Footage: "Fidel NY (part 1) Transfers Cassettes 1-6", undated; cuid18196; 467877 (Box 8, Cassette ref176)
    This footage is most likely associated with the 50th Anniversary of the United Nations.
  - State Council Footage: "Fidel NY (part 3) Transfers Cassettes 9-15", undated; cuid18197; 467876 (Box 8, Cassette ref177)
  - State Council Footage: "Fidel NY (part 4) Transfers Cassettes 15-23", undated; cuid18198; 467875 (Box 8, Cassette ref178)
  - State Council Footage: "Fidel NY (part 5) Transfers Cassettes 23-34", undated; cuid18199; 467874 (Box 8, Cassette ref179)
  - State Council Footage: NY Scenes (NYC), undated; cuid18200; 467861 (Box 9, Cassette ref192)
  - State Council Footage: Fidel Castro in the Bronx, 1995 October 23; cuid18201; 467860 (Box 9, Cassette ref193)
  - State Council Footage: Bronx Jimmy's Cafe, undated; cuid18202; 467850 (Box 9, Cassette ref203)
  - State Council Footage: Castro in Bronx, undated; cuid18203; 467847 (Box 9, Cassette ref206)
    Footage includes scenes of demonstrations outside Jimmy's Cafe and Fidel Castro's motorcade.
  - State Council Footage: IRC Reception (NY) Also meeting religious people with Lucius Walker, 1995; cuid18204; 479357 (Box 47, Cassette ref1018)
    Contains footage of the Cuban Mission reception at the 50th Anniversary of the United Nations in New York.
  - State Council Footage: Demonstrations, undated; cuid383; 479360 (Box 47, Cassette ref1021, Box 95, Dvd ref1021)
    This video features clips of demonstrations celebrating Fidel Castro and Cuba, and others featuring anti-Castro rallies. Rallies featured in this footage were filmed in Uruguay, Bolivia, Chile, Argentina, and New York City. Many demonstrations coincided with a visit by Castro to these locations, and Castro appears in some of the footage. The bulk of the footage features sweeping views of the crowds, but some segments also contain brief on-the-street interviews with participants.
  - State Council Footage: Demonstrations - NYC Peace for Cuba, undated; cuid18205; 467868 (Box 9, Cassette ref185)
  - State Council Footage: "Cuba Demonstrations", 1995 October 21; cuid18206; 467849 (Box 9, Cassette ref204)
  - State Council Footage: Fidel "Starlock/Bravo ETV Archive TeleCine", undated; cuid18207; 479353 (Box 46, Cassette ref1014, Box 98, Dvd ref1014)